<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | cogent free knowledge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-26T15:42:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joel Clermont]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who Is Responsbile for Your Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/05/02/who-is-responsbile-for-your-learning/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T14:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/05/02/who-is-responsbile-for-your-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you expecting too much from an author, speaker or teacher? Take charge of your own learning instead. Consider some tips from a recent <a href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/01/26/learning-how-to-learn-the-newsletter/" target="_blank">"Learning how to Learn" newsletter</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Effective learning is not passive</h2>

<p>My goal with this newsletter is to provide an idea, tip or strategy that you can
immediately put into practice to become a more effective learner. In order to
benefit, though, you need to both <em>read</em> the information and then <em>try it out</em> on
your own. Even if it seems silly, obvious, irrelevant, just try it. Reading
should take no more than 5 - 10 minutes. I will keep each article brief and
focused and give you a link to more information if your curiosity is piqued.</p>

<p>This idea of trying something out is the focus of our first installment. So
often, we approach learning as a passive process. We may not explicitly think
about it that way, but the assumption is there. In fact, it was likely planted
there as a child. Think of how you were taught in school: A teacher lectured,
maybe assigned some additional material to read on your own, and then you were
given homework to demonstrate that you learned the day's lesson. Your job was to
pay attention, ask a question if something was unclear, then go off on your own
and try to reproduce what you learned by completing an assignment.</p>

<p>Now think about how you approach learning today as a professional. You buy a
book, attend a workshop or conference, watch a video. Many times, that's it.
There isn't even any homework to try to prove to yourself that you learned
something. In this approach, just simply taking in information, whether it's by
reading or listening, feels like an accomplishment. I finished that book! I
heard some awesome talks at a conference! I have new knowledge! But do you?
Perhaps you were exposed to some new ideas, but did you really understand them?
Have you applied them to your own projects or problems?</p>

<p>This is where many end up feeling frustrated. They invested their time and
money, but they don't really feel any further ahead than before. Unfortunately,
I'm going to break some bad news: The solution is to actually make yourself more
frustrated. You need to flip the whole process of learning on its head and view
it as an activity that you are driving, not the author or speaker or teacher.</p>

<p>There is a growing movement among college professors, especially in the field of
mathematics, called Inquiry Based Learning. Instead of lecturing or assigning
reading, they start by presenting some very basic facts or definitions, and then
propose problems for the students to solve. Here's the tricky part: they never
explicitly showed the student how to solve the type of problem before.
Initially, many students find this bewildering and frustrating. How can they
possibly solve something they haven't yet been taught to solve? But, as they
persevere and explore the topic through trial and error and discuss it with
fellow students, they do eventually reach the solution. Perhaps it takes them
several classes, or even a couple weeks, but once they've found the solution, it
has a much more profound impact on them. Studies have shown that you are more
likely to remember something you discover in this way than something merely
taught by rote in a lecture or book.</p>

<p>Isn't that what we, as software developers, want? We want to truly gain new
concepts, new ways of thinking, new methods of solving problems. We don't just
want to memorize solutions in hopes that we can apply them to a real-world
problem some day. Here's the catch though: very few software books are written
in this style (see below for an exception). Instead, it's a more traditional
written recitation of facts and information. But, by shifting our mental model
of how learning takes place, we can still apply these same concepts as we learn.</p>

<p><strong>Don't learn too much at once.</strong> Focus on one idea or concept before moving on. In
a typical book, this will often be far less than a single chapter.</p>

<p><strong>Try it out as soon as possible.</strong> Don't cut and paste code, instead try to reimplement it
yourself from memory. If you can't remember, don't immediately go back to the
book or search the Internet. Stick with it, try and fail, experiment, make it
work.</p>

<p><strong>Challenge the author's statements.</strong> Try to prove them wrong. Extend their ideas.
In what situations does it work and it what situations does the solution break
down?</p>

<p><strong>Concepts, not solutions.</strong> The goal is to improve your ability to solve problems,
not to merely solve a contrived set of problems presented in the book. What is
the core idea being taught? Can you restate it? Can you defend it?</p>

<p>Yes, this approach is a lot more work, but that is the point. You are teaching
yourself. You are exploring ideas on your own, thereby really mastering them. In
the end, you will have actually learned something and not just feel like you
should have learned something.</p>

<p>For more information on the concept of Inquiry Based Learning, check out this
video: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f6t6WiWYdgY" target="_blank">Creativity in Mathematics: Inquiry-Based Learning and the Moore Method</a>. If you can get past the cheesy
music and the fact that it's focused on mathematics, you'll see the benefit of
this approach to learning.</p>

<p>Okay, so you read the whole article. Remember that is ONLY step one. Now go, try
this out!</p>

<p>P.S. One notable example of a book taught in the spirit of inquiry-based
learning is <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Little-Schemer-4th-Edition/dp/0262560992" target="_blank">The Little Schemer</a> (and others
in that family). Even if you never plan on writing Scheme/Lisp, I highly
recommend working through this book. It will give you new ways of thinking about
software, ideas that transcend a specific language.</p>

<p>If you enjoyed this article, and want more tips on effective learning for software developers, take 30 seconds and subscribe to my newsletter below.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="http://cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://joelclermont.us4.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=5abeba9688261dbb0d2733fe4&amp;id=ff515965b5" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Become more effective at learning. Subscribe to my newsletter and start improving your skills!</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-FNAME">First Name </label>
    <input type="text" value="" name="FNAME" class="" id="mce-FNAME">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-LNAME">Last Name </label>
    <input type="text" value="" name="LNAME" class="" id="mce-LNAME">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group input-group">
    <strong>Email Format </strong>
    <ul><li><input type="radio" value="html" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-0"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-0">html</label></li>
<li><input type="radio" value="text" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-1"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-1">text</label></li>
<li><input type="radio" value="mobile" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-2"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-2">mobile</label></li>
</ul>
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>  <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';fnames[1]='FNAME';ftypes[1]='text';fnames[2]='LNAME';ftypes[2]='text';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}
var script = document.createElement('script');
script.type = 'text/javascript';
script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
head.appendChild(script);
var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://joelclermont.us4.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post-json?u=5abeba9688261dbb0d2733fe4&id=ff515965b5&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning How to Learn: The Newsletter]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/01/26/learning-how-to-learn-the-newsletter/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-26T03:12:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/01/26/learning-how-to-learn-the-newsletter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Software developers are, by necessity, lifelong learners. We are constantly facing new challenges, new technologies, new methods of solving problems. But how can we make our learning more efficient? This is a question that I've been pondering for at least four years.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I can trace my fascination with this subject back to a book I read in 2009. The book was called <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning" target="_blank">Pragmatic Thinking &amp; Learning</a>. In it, the author pulled together extensive research from the fields of neuroscience, learning/behavioral theory and biology, applying it to challenges we face as software developers. It gave me insights into the process of learning, the actual mechanics of what happens inside the brain. This is the only non-fiction book that I have read twice in a single year. It is that good.</p>

<p>After a couple of years of studying and applying what I had learned from the book, I was convinced that I had not only become more efficient in acquiring new knowledge and skills, but I also had a much better strategy at identifying what things I <em>needed</em> to learn. In addition to identifying my own skill gaps, I was able to look at the vast array of languages, tools and technologies and analyze what new skills would benefit me the most and support my specific goals.</p>

<p>The next logical step was to begin sharing what I had learned with others. I submitted a talk entitled "Learning How to Learn" to several conferences, each time being rejected. I finally got my break at <a href="http://midwestphp.com" target="_blank">Midwest PHP</a> in March 2013. While the organizers initially rejected my talk proposal, they later approached me and asked me if I would consider giving this talk as the opening keynote. I was thrilled and the audience response was phenomenal. You can see some of the <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/8196" target="_blank">feedback I received on joind.in</a>. I know I'm biased, but I think this subject is something that should be discussed at every conference. People are there to learn, so having a talk devoted to becoming a more effective learner seems like an obvious fit. Despite that, and despite having submitted it at several conferences since Midwest PHP, it continues to be rejected.</p>

<p>Not content to wait for the next conference willing to accept my talk, I've decided to take matters into my own hands to share this valuable message with my fellow developers. For the last several months, I've been working on an ebook that will take everything I've learned in my research and distill it into bite-sized pieces of information that anyone can put into practice for themselves. While the information is applicable to any type of learning, I'm keeping a razor focus on learning within the context of software development. This is where my energy has been directed and this is where all my experimentation and practice has been applied. By staying focused on this particular context, I believe I can make a more profound impact on those that read the book.</p>

<p>Writing (and researching) the book is a time-consuming process though, and I'm chomping at the bit to share some information NOW. Because of this, I am announcing a weekly newsletter. Each week, I will deliver a specific tip or strategy you can use right away. Each newsletter article will take only 5 - 10 minutes to read, but if you make that investment and actually try to apply the information, you will become a more effective learner. I also plan on including an additional reference on each topic to give you further things to explore. Think of it as an annotated bibliography for the book I will eventually release.</p>

<p>If you're still unsure if this is something you'd find useful, consider the following statements. Do any of them resonate with you?</p>

<ul>
<li>I know I've been a developer for years, but I still don't feel like I've really mastered this. Sometimes, I feel like an "impostor."</li>
<li>Sure, I know "Technology X", but that's all I know. I feel trapped by my own skills and want to branch out.</li>
<li>I really want to learn "Technology X", but I don't have the time.</li>
<li>I've tried learning "Technology X", but I don't know where to start.</li>
<li>I've tried learning "Technology X", but I'm not making any progress. It's in one ear and out the other.</li>
<li>Things change too fast in this field. I can't keep up with it all!</li>
</ul>


<p>In addition, I'd ask that you please <em>share this article</em> with your friends and coworkers. Share it on Twitter and Facebook. Talk about it at your user groups. Spread the word. Yes, I have an ulterior motive: I want to get people excited in the topic so they'll eventually buy my book. But, I also genuinely feel this is something that <em>many</em> developers struggle with. I've been there and I've overcome the challenges listed above. Now I want to share what I've learned with as many developers as possible and help them overcome these same challenges as well.</p>

<p>Please take 30 seconds now and sign up for the weekly newsletter. The first issue will be sent on Monday, February 3.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="http://cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://joelclermont.us4.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=5abeba9688261dbb0d2733fe4&amp;id=ff515965b5" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Become more effective at learning. Subscribe to my weekly newsletter and start improving your skills!</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-FNAME">First Name </label>
    <input type="text" value="" name="FNAME" class="" id="mce-FNAME">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-LNAME">Last Name </label>
    <input type="text" value="" name="LNAME" class="" id="mce-LNAME">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group input-group">
    <strong>Email Format </strong>
    <ul><li><input type="radio" value="html" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-0"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-0">html</label></li>
<li><input type="radio" value="text" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-1"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-1">text</label></li>
<li><input type="radio" value="mobile" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-2"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-2">mobile</label></li>
</ul>
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>  <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';fnames[1]='FNAME';ftypes[1]='text';fnames[2]='LNAME';ftypes[2]='text';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}
var script = document.createElement('script');
script.type = 'text/javascript';
script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
head.appendChild(script);
var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://joelclermont.us4.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post-json?u=5abeba9688261dbb0d2733fe4&id=ff515965b5&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
