<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conferences | cogent free knowledge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/categories/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-26T16:00:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joel Clermont]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A modern approach to PHP development]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2013/08/14/a-modern-approach-to-php-development/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-14T02:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2013/08/14/a-modern-approach-to-php-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year at <a href="http://www.thatconference.com">That Conference</a>, I presented one of the few talks on PHP. The title of the talk was "<a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jclermont/a-modern-approach-to-php-development">A modern approach to PHP development</a>." My goal was to expose both PHP and non-PHP developers to some more recent developments in the PHP ecosystem.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Speaking of non-PHP developers, I was pleasantly surprised to see about a dozen .NET developers attend the talk. The opening keynote that day was by Dave Thomas and he promoted the idea of exposing yourself to things outside your normal interests. I know for myself, I really enjoy attending polyglot conferences for that very reason.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jclermont/a-modern-approach-to-php-development">slides</a> are posted on Speaker Deck. I have to warn you in advance that very little content is in the slides. Most of it was me speaking from my experience on how I've used the tools and how they made my development more efficient, higher quality and more fun. I did type up some speaker notes and exported those as part of the slide deck, to give a little context to the slides.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at WordCamp Milwaukee]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/05/22/speaking-at-wordcamp-milwaukee/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-22T09:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/05/22/speaking-at-wordcamp-milwaukee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick note that I'll be speaking at WordCamp Milwaukee on June 3. The talk is titled "Contributing to Open Source Projects". It's not really a WordPress specific topic, but more of a general encouragement for everyone to get involved in open source and how specifically to go about it. Read the <a href="http://2012.milwaukee.wordcamp.org/session/contributing-to-open-source-projects/">official brief on the WordCamp site</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Also, if you haven't purchased a ticket yet and you would like to attend, I have a discount code that will bring the already cheap $20 price down to $10. Use the code wcspeaker when <a href="http://2012.milwaukee.wordcamp.org/tickets/">buying a ticket</a>. See you there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Onsite for CodeMash]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/01/09/onsite-for-codemash/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-09T00:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/01/09/onsite-for-codemash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the next week, I'm going to be adding quite a few short posts chronicling my experience at the <a href="http://codemash.org">CodeMash</a> conference. The event is a few years old, but this is the first year I'm attending.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Just arriving at the Kalahari resort, I can already tell this is going to be quite unlike any conference I've previously attended. I had a 7 hour drive from Milwaukee, so I headed straight to my room to crash, but I'll be exploring the facility more tomorrow. Speaking of the rooms, I was pleasantly surprised at how spacious it was and all the amenities I had, especially considering the low rate. Kudos to the organizers for getting such a great deal for attendees.</p>

<p>CodeMash doesn't even start until Wednesday, so I have two days to bulk up on sleep and get the lay of the land. If you're attending, drop me a note and let's get together for a meal or just some drinks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally, a PHP conference in Wisconsin!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2011/08/04/finally-a-php-conference-in-wisconsin/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-04T16:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2011/08/04/finally-a-php-conference-in-wisconsin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm a huge fan of <a href="http://www.phparch.com/">php|architect</a>: the magazine, the books, the online training and especially their conferences. Living in the Milwaukee metro area, I have a short 90 minute drive to the flagship <a href="http://tek.phparch.com/">php|tek conference</a> they host in Chicago each year. My schedule doesn't always allow me to attend, but I do everything I can to make it. I'm still putting into practice the things I learned at php|tek 2010 and I regularly keep in touch with the many friends I met there.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>That being said, it came as a very welcome surprise today when I opened my mail and found an invitation to <a href="http://codeworks.phparch.com/">CodeWorks 2011</a> in Madison, Wisconsin! CodeWorks is a single-day, single track conference focused on PHP, but historically, it's stayed pretty far away from Wisconsin. I suspect this is because we already have php|tek in our backyard, but I always lobbied hard to have a CodeWorks stop near us as well. Let's face it: not everyone can take a week off work to attend php|tek, not to mention the travel and hotel expenses. Don't get me wrong, it's worth every cent, but for those that haven't experienced it firsthand, it may be a big pill to swallow.</p>

<p>With a CodeWorks coming to my home state, I am going to sing (or at least blog) about it from the rooftops. I want the Madison event to be a success so there's a higher likelihood it may return in 2012. I'll be preaching about it at our next several <a href="http://www.mkepug.org/">Milwaukee PHP meetings</a>, as well as on <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jclermont">Twitter</a>. With the low cost and the location, if you are a PHP developer in southern Wisconsin (or even northern Wisconsin or Minneapolis), you have run out of excuses not to attend.</p>

<p><a href="http://codeworks.phparch.com/east-coast-tour/madison-wi-december-1-2011/">Get your ticket</a> by August 13 and it's only $60. What are you waiting for? Go sign up now and I'll see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
