<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: news | cogent free knowledge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-23T20:02:22-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joel Clermont]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning How to Learn: The Newsletter]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/01/26/learning-how-to-learn-the-newsletter/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-26T03:12:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2014/01/26/learning-how-to-learn-the-newsletter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Software developers are, by necessity, lifelong learners. We are constantly facing new challenges, new technologies, new methods of solving problems. But how can we make our learning more efficient? This is a question that I've been pondering for at least four years.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I can trace my fascination with this subject back to a book I read in 2009. The book was called <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning" target="_blank">Pragmatic Thinking &amp; Learning</a>. In it, the author pulled together extensive research from the fields of neuroscience, learning/behavioral theory and biology, applying it to challenges we face as software developers. It gave me insights into the process of learning, the actual mechanics of what happens inside the brain. This is the only non-fiction book that I have read twice in a single year. It is that good.</p>

<p>After a couple of years of studying and applying what I had learned from the book, I was convinced that I had not only become more efficient in acquiring new knowledge and skills, but I also had a much better strategy at identifying what things I <em>needed</em> to learn. In addition to identifying my own skill gaps, I was able to look at the vast array of languages, tools and technologies and analyze what new skills would benefit me the most and support my specific goals.</p>

<p>The next logical step was to begin sharing what I had learned with others. I submitted a talk entitled "Learning How to Learn" to several conferences, each time being rejected. I finally got my break at <a href="http://midwestphp.com" target="_blank">Midwest PHP</a> in March 2013. While the organizers initially rejected my talk proposal, they later approached me and asked me if I would consider giving this talk as the opening keynote. I was thrilled and the audience response was phenomenal. You can see some of the <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/8196" target="_blank">feedback I received on joind.in</a>. I know I'm biased, but I think this subject is something that should be discussed at every conference. People are there to learn, so having a talk devoted to becoming a more effective learner seems like an obvious fit. Despite that, and despite having submitted it at several conferences since Midwest PHP, it continues to be rejected.</p>

<p>Not content to wait for the next conference willing to accept my talk, I've decided to take matters into my own hands to share this valuable message with my fellow developers. For the last several months, I've been working on an ebook that will take everything I've learned in my research and distill it into bite-sized pieces of information that anyone can put into practice for themselves. While the information is applicable to any type of learning, I'm keeping a razor focus on learning within the context of software development. This is where my energy has been directed and this is where all my experimentation and practice has been applied. By staying focused on this particular context, I believe I can make a more profound impact on those that read the book.</p>

<p>Writing (and researching) the book is a time-consuming process though, and I'm chomping at the bit to share some information NOW. Because of this, I am announcing a weekly newsletter. Each week, I will deliver a specific tip or strategy you can use right away. Each newsletter article will take only 5 - 10 minutes to read, but if you make that investment and actually try to apply the information, you will become a more effective learner. I also plan on including an additional reference on each topic to give you further things to explore. Think of it as an annotated bibliography for the book I will eventually release.</p>

<p>If you're still unsure if this is something you'd find useful, consider the following statements. Do any of them resonate with you?</p>

<ul>
<li>I know I've been a developer for years, but I still don't feel like I've really mastered this. Sometimes, I feel like an "impostor."</li>
<li>Sure, I know "Technology X", but that's all I know. I feel trapped by my own skills and want to branch out.</li>
<li>I really want to learn "Technology X", but I don't have the time.</li>
<li>I've tried learning "Technology X", but I don't know where to start.</li>
<li>I've tried learning "Technology X", but I'm not making any progress. It's in one ear and out the other.</li>
<li>Things change too fast in this field. I can't keep up with it all!</li>
</ul>


<p>In addition, I'd ask that you please <em>share this article</em> with your friends and coworkers. Share it on Twitter and Facebook. Talk about it at your user groups. Spread the word. Yes, I have an ulterior motive: I want to get people excited in the topic so they'll eventually buy my book. But, I also genuinely feel this is something that <em>many</em> developers struggle with. I've been there and I've overcome the challenges listed above. Now I want to share what I've learned with as many developers as possible and help them overcome these same challenges as well.</p>

<p>Please take 30 seconds now and sign up for the weekly newsletter. The first issue will be sent on Monday, February 3.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="http://cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://joelclermont.us4.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=5abeba9688261dbb0d2733fe4&amp;id=ff515965b5" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Become more effective at learning. Subscribe to my weekly newsletter and start improving your skills!</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-FNAME">First Name </label>
    <input type="text" value="" name="FNAME" class="" id="mce-FNAME">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-LNAME">Last Name </label>
    <input type="text" value="" name="LNAME" class="" id="mce-LNAME">
</div>
<div class="mc-field-group input-group">
    <strong>Email Format </strong>
    <ul><li><input type="radio" value="html" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-0"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-0">html</label></li>
<li><input type="radio" value="text" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-1"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-1">text</label></li>
<li><input type="radio" value="mobile" name="EMAILTYPE" id="mce-EMAILTYPE-2"><label for="mce-EMAILTYPE-2">mobile</label></li>
</ul>
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>  <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';fnames[1]='FNAME';ftypes[1]='text';fnames[2]='LNAME';ftypes[2]='text';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}
var script = document.createElement('script');
script.type = 'text/javascript';
script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
head.appendChild(script);
var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://joelclermont.us4.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post-json?u=5abeba9688261dbb0d2733fe4&id=ff515965b5&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[30x500 Orientation]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/10/13/30x500-orientation/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-13T17:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/10/13/30x500-orientation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently enrolled in <a href="http://unicornfree.com/30x500/">30x500</a>, an online class designed to teach you how to launch successful products. I know how to run a consulting business (been there, done that) and I know how to build software applications, but I had no real idea how to build and launch a product. After <a href="https://twitter.com/jclermont/status/250635149824360449">tweeting about my enrollment</a>, a few people responded with curiosity, intrigued at the idea, but not yet ready to put down the money to join. <a href="https://twitter.com/jclermont/status/257103933389033472">Today was orientation</a>, so I decided to start documenting my experiences right away, not only for my own benefit, but also for those perhaps on the fence about taking this class themselves.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Orientation began with the instructors introducing themselves. <a href="https://twitter.com/amyhoy">Amy Hoy</a> and <a href="http://alexhillman.com">Alex Hillman</a>, the course creators, were joined by <a href="https://twitter.com/brennandunn">Brennan Dunn</a>, a former alumnus of the course. Speaking of alumni, there were a lot of them taking the course again. One of the interesting aspects of 30x500 is that you can re-enroll in the course at any point in the future with no additional cost. Enrolling again isn't a sign that the course is ineffective, it's a sign of just how dense it is with information and how supportive and amazing the community is.</p>

<p>One of the words I noticed come up more than once was "frenetic." You could sense the enthusiasm of the new students taking the course for the first time (myself included). We were all eager to get started and dive in, even though the official first day of class isn't until November 5. "Frenetic" also applies to the level of effort put into the course by the instructors. You might think that since the course has run several times before, they might be on auto-pilot, but quite the opposite is true. In fact, the three of them completely revamped the course from the Summer 2012 semester. For example, instead of a 12-week arc, this has been refactored into two cycles of 6 weeks each. The alumni in the room were pretty excited at this propsect, so the instructors must be on to something here.</p>

<p>While there was a lot of information to absorb today, I came away with two key lessons from today's orientation:</p>

<ol>
<li>DO THE WORK. No, seriously, do all the work. Students are tempted to cherry pick what "makes sense" to them or skip over things that seem unimportant, but this is a recipe for failure.</li>
<li>Unlearn what you have learned. Many of the students have either tried to launch a product before or have a head full of ideas for products they want to build. The instructors repeatedly emphasized the need to push that aside and focus on the 30x500 method.</li>
</ol>


<p>Outside of these two main lessons, I made note of a few smaller nuggets of wisdom:</p>

<ol>
<li>Don't be afraid of people copying you. This might be a natural response since we're all in the class to launch a product, but the instructors were quite firm in allaying this fear.</li>
<li>Practice writing. On paper. This is a skill that I let atrophy, but I'm going to need it for 30x500. I'm taking all my notes by hand in a notebook, not in a text editor. While I'll be summarizing things on my blog, that is just more practice writing and summarizing, but not my primary means of capturing information.</li>
<li>Build and cultivate tiny habits. Early on, we were recommended to participate in Dr. BJ Fogg's <a href="http://tinyhabits.com" target="_blank">Tiny Habits</a> program. I'll be honest, it seemed overly simplistic to me, but I gave it a try the first week. I'm now hooked. I'll definitely be posting more on this topic in the future, but the quick feedback loop of setting and meeting a few tiny habits is surprisingly life changing.</li>
</ol>


<p>Our first reading assignment will arrive on Tuesday and I'll be continuing to journal my experiences here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contributing to Open Source Projects (slides)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/06/03/contributing-to-open-source-projects-slides/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-03T16:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/06/03/contributing-to-open-source-projects-slides</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to everyone who attended my talk today, especially those that asked questions and gave me feedback afterwards.</p>

<p>I'm posting my slides for the talk I gave at WordCamp Milwaukee today. As with most talks, there is a lot more information than what the slides contain, but at least it is something.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I also heard that the video recording of my talk will be posted to wordcamp.tv at some point too. Once I get that link I'll post it here.</p>

<p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jclermont/contributing-to-open-source">Download slides (PDF)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at WordCamp Milwaukee]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/05/22/speaking-at-wordcamp-milwaukee/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-22T09:10:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.joelclermont.com/2012/05/22/speaking-at-wordcamp-milwaukee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick note that I'll be speaking at WordCamp Milwaukee on June 3. The talk is titled "Contributing to Open Source Projects". It's not really a WordPress specific topic, but more of a general encouragement for everyone to get involved in open source and how specifically to go about it. Read the <a href="http://2012.milwaukee.wordcamp.org/session/contributing-to-open-source-projects/">official brief on the WordCamp site</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Also, if you haven't purchased a ticket yet and you would like to attend, I have a discount code that will bring the already cheap $20 price down to $10. Use the code wcspeaker when <a href="http://2012.milwaukee.wordcamp.org/tickets/">buying a ticket</a>. See you there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
